Finding aid for the One East 70th Street Papers, 1907-1931 HCFF.7
The Frick Collection/Frick Art Reference Library Archives
- Series II: Construction Notes and Correspondence, 1912-1918
  - Johnson & Morris, 1913-1914 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Analysis of account, including labor, materials, and outside dealers.
  - Lord Electric Co., 1914-1916 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Anaylsis of account, including labor, materials, and outside dealers.
  - McElroy, F.W., 1912-1915 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
    Chiefly correspondence from D.B. Kinch updating Frick on construction progress. Also includes letters to and/or from J. B. Eustis, Charles Carstairs, Carrère & Hastings, and White, Allom & Co.
  - McNulty Bros., Inc., 1913-1914 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Audit of account for plastering contractor.
  - W. & J. Sloane, 1914-1915 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - White, Allom & Co., 1913 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Includes correspondence with Carrère & Hastings, schedule of interior finish for One East 70th Street, and insurance policies.
  - White, Allom & Co., continued, 1914-1916 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - William Bradley & Son, 1913-1914 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Includes lists of changes to exterior stone work, correspondence to/from Carrère & Hastings, and estimates for models and stone work, with references to a proposed stone fountain that was never constructed. Also contains letter from Carrère & Hastings re: distribution of contracts for iron grilles amongst three different firms.
  - Letterpress copybook, 1912-1918 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Contains 476 pages of outgoing correspondence from Frick re: the construction and furnishing of One East 70th Street, with alphabetical index of correspondents at the front of the volume. Includes correspondence with his superintendent, D.B. Kinch, architect Thomas Hastings of Carrère & Hastings, Bankers Trust Co., Charles Carstairs of M. Knoedler and Co., Charles Allom of White, Allom & Co., Elsie de Wolfe, Duveen Brothers, and various contractors, dealers, and at least one member of the press. Also includes cumulative lists of contracts awarded throughout the construction process.
- Series III: Construction Special Orders, 1913-1915
  This series documents special orders for work not included among the general contracts in Series I. Folder contents typically include correspondence regarding proposals and acceptances, special order certificates issued by the architect, construction specifications, and itemized bills.
  Arranged alphabetically by contractor. For a list of special orders arranged by number, see folder containing lists of special orders issued by the architect in this series.
  - Lists of special orders issued by architect, 1913-1914 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Chronological lists of special orders, including name of contractor, work ordered, and cost.
  - Brunswick-Balke-Collender Co., 1914 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    For furnishing and installing bowling alleys (Special order No. 260).
  - Cauldwell-Wingate Co., 1913-1915 (Box 11, Folder 3-9)
    For kalamein window frames, repairs and maintenance on the construction site, foundation masonry and accompanying work, curb and sidewalks, carpentry, waterproofing, etc.
  - Diebold Safe & Lock Co., 1914-1915 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    For furnishing and installing two safes.
  - Edward F. Caldwell & Co., 1914-1915 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    For screen in North Hall, electric ceiling fixtures at the entrance door, credits in connection with the lattice wall and bird screen, and gold mesh screens in the lower part of the organ screen.
  - Fry, Sherry E., 1913 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Model for sculptural work on one pediment
  - Henderson Brothers, 1914 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Opal glass and frame for organ console
  - Henry Bonnard Bronze Co., 1913-1914 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Hardware for bronze basement windows; cast bronze frame and sash.
  - Interior Metal Manufacturing Co., 1913-1914 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Installation, alteration, and finishing of doors.
  - John Morrow Co., 1913-1914 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Work in connection with roofing and skylights.
  - John H. Shipway & Brother, 1913-1915 (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
    Tile and slate work; marble pedestals for bust and candelabra. Folder contains specifications for tile work throughout the residence.
  - John Williams, Inc., 1914 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Alterations to 71st Street fence, twenty-six feet of area rail, polished steel grille for West Vestibule entrance, etc.
  - Keck, Charles, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Model for sculptural work on one pediment.
  - Lenygon & Morant, Inc., 1914 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Marble mantel for Helen Clay Frick's Bedroom.
  - Martiny, Philip, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Menconi Brothers, 1914-1915 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    Plaster casts of wrought iron grills, doors, organ screen, vase, pedestal, and standard for candelabra.
  - Morten & Co., 1913-1915 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Wine cellar and wines, etc.
  - Mosler Safe Co., 1914 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Furnishing and installing silver safe.
  - National District Telegraph Co., 1913-1914 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Bronze covers for fire alarm boxes.
  - Neumann & Even, 1913-1914 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Models for interior marble and wood carving, metal casting, ornamentation on stair sting of main staircase, and perforated ceiling over the organ.
  - Nicholson & Galloway, 1915 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Repair of urn in courtyard.
  - Otis Elevator Co., 1913-1914 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Work in connection with elevators, and hand-powered garbage lift.
  - Piccirilli Brothers, 1913-1914 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Models for marble carving, pediments, vaulted ceiling, and main stair hall; superintending of stone carving.
  - Sangiorgi Gallery, 1915 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Antique velvet to be made into pillows and table cover.
  - Todhunter, Arthur, 1913-1914 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    For nine mantels and set of old Ashburton marble mouldings.
  - W. & J. Sloane, 1913-1915 (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
    Plaster models, wood carving, and additional interior finishing. Includes specifications for woodwork, etc., in Billiard Room, stair ceiling, stair rails, and elevator car.
  - Western Union Telegraph Co., 1914 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Installation of stock ticker.
  - White, Allom & Co., 1914-1915 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Wrought iron railing of main staircase, and organ case of carved wood.
  - William Bradley & Son, 1913-1914 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Exterior limestone work; furnishing and setting of Royal Blue Indiana limestone and Pink Tennessee marble on the grounds. Includes specifications for limestone, marble, and masonry work.
  - Wm. H. Jackson Co., 1914-1915 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Additional work in connection with wrought iron fence; overtime for work on stair railing and chimney dampers.
  - Yale & Towne Manufacturing Co., 1913-1915 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Hardware for doors, windows, closets, etc.
  - Yellin, Samuel, 1913-1914 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    For drawings and samples for ornamental iron work, and wrought iron hardware.
- Series IV: Construction Vouchers, 1912-1914
  This series consists of payment vouchers issued to firms, agencies, and individuals during the construction of the Frick residence at One East 70th Street. As was typical of Henry Clay Frick's accounting practices (see Henry Clay Frick Papers, Series III: Voucher Files for additional examples), vouchers were prepared and sent to the payee along with a check for the amount owed. These vouchers were receipted by the payee, and returned to Henry Clay Frick for his files as evidence of remittance received. Vouchers may have correspondence, invoices, or related documentation attached.
  Arranged by voucher number; an alphabetical index of voucher recipients is filed at the beginning of the series.
  - Voucher index, 1912-1914 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Index of vouchers issued during the construction of One East 70th Street. Names of firms, agencies, people, etc. are listed alphabetically.
  - Vouchers 1-35, 1912-1913 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Vouchers issues between September 1912 and May 1913 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: Travelers Insurance Co.; John H. Tripler, Inc.; Piccirilli Bros.; A. Shelton; Davis & Warde; Joseph P. Day; Simpson, Thacher & Bartlett; Canavan Brothers Co.; Wadley & Smythe; William Bradley & Son; Borough of Manhattan; Carrère & Hastings; Gordon & Smith; New York City Dept. of Water Supply, Gas, and Electricity; H.C. Frick; James Elgar, Inc.; American Bridge Co. of New York; Johnson & Morris; and Cauldwell-Wingate Co.
  - Vouchers 36-70, 1913 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Vouchers issued between May and October 1913 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; William Bradley & Son; J.N. Knight & Son; Canavan Brothers Co.; Carrère & Hastings; American Bridge Co. of New York; James Elgar, Inc.; Johnson & Morris; John Morrow Co.; and Piccirilli Brothers
  - Vouchers 71-95, 1913 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Vouchers issued between October and December 1913 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; John Morrow Co.; Canavan Brothers Co.; William Bradley & Son, J.N. Knight & Son; Johnson & Morris; Lord Electric Co.; American Bridge Co. of New York; White, Allom & Co.; John H. Shipway & Brother; Carrère & Hastings; Neumann & Even; Arthur Todhunter; Philip Martiny; and Charles Keck
  - Vouchers 96-125, 1913-1914 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Vouchers issued between December 1913 and January 1914 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: Sherry E. Fry; Piccirilli Brothers; Carrère & Hastings; Arthur Todhunter; Johnson & Morris; John Morrow Co.; J.N. Knight & Son; Otis Elevator Co.; Neumann & Even; Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; McNulty Brothers, Inc.; Carrère & Hastings; William Bradley & Son; White, Allom & Co.; New York Steam Co.; Pittsburgh Plate Glass Co.; American Bridge Co. of New York; H.C. Frick; Johnson & Morris; and John H. Shipway & Brother
  - Vouchers 126-150, 1914 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Vouchers issued between January and March 1914 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: Carrère & Hastings; John H. Shipway & Brother; Wadley & Smythe; Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; Piccirilli Brothers; Charles Keck; Pittsburgh Plate Glass Co.; New York Steam Co.; Johnson & Morris; J.N. Knight & Son; American Bridge Co. of New York; Arthur Todhunter; John Morrow Co.; Samuel Yellin; White, Allom & Co.; and McNulty Brothers, Inc.
  - Vouchers 151-180, 1914 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Voucher issued between March and May 1914 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: Pittsburgh Plate Glass Co.; New York Steam Co.; Carrère & Hastings; W. & J. Sloane; White, Allom & Co.; Interior Metal Manufacturing Co.; Yale & Towne Mfg. Co.; Johnson & Morris; Otis Elevator Co.; Philip Martiny; Henry-Bonnard Bronze Co.; Piccirilli Brothers; Sherry E. Fry; John H. Shipway & Brother; J.N. Knight & Son; Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; McNulty Brothers, Inc.; Neumann & Even; Hill-Canton Dryer Co.; and New York Edison Co.
  - Vouchers 181-205, 1914 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Vouchers issued between May and June 1914 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: H.C. Frick; White, Allom & Co.; John H. Shipway & Brother; New York Steam Co.; Pittsburgh Plate Glass Co.; McNulty Brothers, Inc.; W. & J. Sloane; Johnson & Morris; J.N. Knight & Son; Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; Menconi Brothers; Charles Keck; Carrère & Hastings; American Bridge Co. of New York; Morten & Co.; C.P. Davite; Otis Elevator Co.; Piccirilli Brothers; Yale & Towne Mfg. Co.; and Post & McCord, Inc.
  - Vouchers 206-250, 1914 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Vouchers issued between June and October 1914 to the following firms, agencies, etc.: John H. Shipway & Brother; Duparquet, Hout & Moneuse Co.; McNulty Brothers, Inc.; J.N. Knight & Son; Johnson & Morris; Cauldwell-Wingate Co.; John Williams, Inc.; Carrère & Hastings; W. & J. Sloane; Hill-Canton Dryer Co.; Menconi Brothers; Sherry E. Fry; John Morrow Co.; Otis Elevator Co.; Jewett Refrigerator Co.; Post & McCord, Inc.; New York Steam Co.; Piccirilli Brothers; Yale & Towne Mfg. Co.; Neumann & Even; New York Edison Co.; Wm. Bradley & Son; Wm. H. Jackson Co.; New York Edison Co.; Philip Martiny; J.N. Knight & Son; C.P. Davite; Arthur Todhunter; and Lenygon & Morant, Inc.
- Series V: Furnishings, 1914-1924, undated
  This series contains lists of contracts and estimates, as well as letters, telegrams, notes, and invoices pertaining to the furnishing and decoration of One East 70th Street. As the principal decorators for the house, the files of White, Allom & Co. and Elsie de Wolfe comprise the bulk of this series. Their invoices and correspondence document the procurement of carpets, draperies, mantelpieces, furniture, wall coverings, light fixtures, and accessories for the house. Charles Allom's earliest letters discuss his plans for decorative treatment of various rooms, while later correspondence responds to Henry Clay Frick's frustration at work on the house that remained unfinished. Allom's files also document the changes to the Drawing Room after Frick's acquisition of the Fragonard panels in 1915. Elsie de Wolfe's letters detail the selection of antique pieces through various dealers in London and Paris. Other decorators, dealers, and contractors represented in this series include Duveen Brothers, through whom Frick purchased artwork and furnishings from the J.P. Morgan Collection, E.R. Bacon, who facilitated the purchase of a suite of Beauvais tapestry furniture from the Duke of Devonshire and supplied a set of antique silver wine coolers for the Dining Room, Maus, who overhauled the suite of tapestry furniture, and Gerald and Sydney Letts, who furnished the Bowling Alley and Billiard Room.
  Additional material concerning the acquisition of objects from the Morgan Collection can be found in the Henry Clay Frick Papers, Series I: Art Files; the Eagle Rock Papers, Series: Furnishings; and the Henry Clay Frick Art Collection Files, all in this repository.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by decorator, dealer, or contractor.
  - Lists of contracts and estimates, 1914-1915 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Includes name of contractor, work contracted for, cost, and amount paid.
  - Bacon, E.R., 1914-1915 (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
    Antique silver wine coolers; suite of tapestry furniture purchased from the Duke of Devonshire.
  - De Wolfe, Elsie, 1914-1915 (Box 16, Folder 4-11)
    For decoration of the Ladies' Reception Room (now the Boucher Room), and most of the second and third floor rooms, with the exception of the Breakfast Room and Henry Clay Frick's Sitting Room. Includes correspondence from de Wolfe and her staff, as well as invoices for furnishings, draperies, and carpet. Invoices reflect furnishings purchased in England from Sir Sidney Greville, S.J. Phillips, Basil Dighton, Lenygon & Morant, Frank Partridge, Charles, S. E. Letts, A.B. Danielle & Sons, Mallet & Son, and Phillips Ltd.; and in France from Stettiner, Bagues Freres, Edouard Jonas & Freres, Arnold Seligman, Doucet, Audrain, Lepeltier, Mathelin, Lewis & Simmons, Edward Larcade, and Jansen.
  - De Wolfe, Elsie, continued, 1916-1924 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
  - Duveen Brothers, 1915-1916 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
    Includes correspondence and invoices re: porcelains and furniture purchased from the Morgan Collection and other sources, as well as outlays in connection with the Fragonard Room. Items marked "N.Y." on these invoices were designated for One East 70th Street; items marked "P.C." were purchased for the Frick country house in Prides Crossing, Mass.
  - Letts, Gerald A. and Sydney E., 1914-1917 (Box 17, Folder 5-6)
    Furnishings for Bowling Alley, Billiard Room, and Office.
  - Maus (Paris, France), 1914-1915 (Box 17, Folder 7-8)
    Includes correspondence with Alfred Anson, Edward R. Bacon, and Walter Rathbone Bacon re: suite of tapestry furniture purchased from the Duke of Devonshire, and refinishing of the suite by Maus of Paris.
  - Morgan, J.P., Jr., 1915 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    For a large carved walnut table of XVI century Italian workmanship; includes letter from J.P. Morgan, Jr.
  - Seligmann, Jacques, 1914-1915 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence re: furnishings purchased, as well as pieces considered but ultimately not purchased. Objects acquired include articles for Adelaide Frick's Boudoir and Bedroom, as well as the Library.
  - W. & J. Sloane Co., 1913-1914 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Correspondence re: proposals to decorate and furnish rooms at One East 70th Street, including the Billiard Room and Bowling Alley.
  - White, Allom & Co., 1913-1916 (Box 18, Folder 3-11)
    Folders contain correspondence and invoices re: principal furnishings for the first floor of the residence, the Breakfast Room and Henry Clay Frick's Sitting Room on the second floor, and changes to the Drawing Room after the purchase of the Fragonard panels. Includes letters to and/or from Charles Allom, Thomas Hastings, and D.B. Kinch.
  - White, Allom & Co., continued, 1917-1921, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - Vouchers for miscellaneous furnishings and household goods, 1914-1919 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Folder contains preservation photocopies of vouchers documenting the purchase of furniture, silver, rugs and textiles, porcelain and glassware, and other household items. Sources for these goods include E.R. Bacon, Crichton Brothers, Duveen Brothers, Grande Maison de Blanc, Tiffany and Co., Elsie de Wolfe, Jacques Seligmann, Sidney E. Letts, and American Art Association, among others. For corresponding original vouchers, see: Henry Clay Frick Papers, Series III: Voucher Files.
- Series VI: Financial Records, 1907-1918
  This series documents expenditures made during the construction and furnishing of One East 70th Street. Along with a summary of costs associated with the purchase of the property, this series contains canceled checks, monthly statements, and a check register from the Bankers Trust Co. special account established by Frick for the purpose of paying construction expenses. Also included in this series are a cash book, journal, ledger in which construction expenses were recorded by Frick's staff. For day-to-day expenses at One East 70th after construction was completed, see Series VIII: Daily Life.
  Items are arranged by material type.
  - New York Library Property, 1907-1911 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Analysis of payments and interest on the property from 2 January 1907 to 1 May 1911.
  - Bankers Trust Co. Special Account - Canceled checks #141-250, 1914 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Bankers Trust Co. Special Account - Canceled checks #276-410, 1914-1918 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Bankers Trust Co. Special Account - Monthly statements, 1914-1918 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Bankers Trust Co. Special Account - Check register, 1914-1918 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Contains stubs for checks #301-410.
  - Construction cash book and journal, 1912-1918 (Box 21, Folder -)
    Dual-purpose volume, with folios 1-99 designated as a cash book, and folios 200-300 as a journal. Cash book entries show debits and credits against the bank account established by Frick at the start of the construction of his New York residence. Journal entries give the name of the contractor being paid, and the nature of the work completed.
  - Construction ledger, 1912-1918 (Box 21, Folder -)
    Ledger in which expenses for the construction and furnishing of the New York Residence are grouped by the type of work commissioned. Categories include electric installation, supplementary interior finish, grilles and gates, and plate glass. An alphabetical index at the front of the volume lists these categories, along with the names of contractors who worked on the house.
- Series VII: Post-Construction and Estate Matters, 1914-1924
  This series contains inventories of the contents of One East 70th Street as well as Frick's garage property located at 129 West 51st Street. Inventories are grouped by type, namely collection property (i.e. items that would become part of The Frick Collection), estate property (items that became part of Frick's estate for distribution under the terms of his will), and personal property (items that were considered the personal property of Adelaide Frick and her daughter Helen). Additional materials in this series include specifications and contracts for the construction of the Frick Art Reference Library (referred to here as the 71st Street Extension), a file on the disposition of frames from the suite of Chatsworth furniture purchased in 1914, a file on the sculpture gallery proposed by Thomas Hastings but never constructed, a dispute with the city re: flagstones outside the residence, and documentation of a claim against W. & J. Sloane re: outstanding remittance for goods removed from the residence and sold.
  Materials are arranged by subject.
  - 71st Street extension [Frick Art Reference Library], 1923-1924 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    Contains specifications and contracts for heating, plumbing, electrical work, and general construction.
  - Chatsworth suite, 1914-1924 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Correspondence re: suite of furniture purchased from the Duke of Devonshire in 1914, and refurbished by Maus in Paris.
  - Estate inventory - correspondence, 1920-1924 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence with Karl F. Overholt, Childs Frick, James Howard Bridge, Josephine Kneisel (employee of Elsie de Wolfe), and W. J. Naughton re: compiling estate inventories after Henry Clay Frick's death.
  - Estate inventory - collection property, [1920] (Box 22, Folder 5)
    List of items at One East 70th Street designated as property of The Frick Collection.
  - Estate inventory - estate property, [1920] (Box 22, Folder 6)
    List of items at One East 70th Street designated as part of Henry Clay Frick's estate to be distributed under the terms of his will.
  - Estate inventory - garage property, 1920 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    Contents of Henry Clay Frick's New York garage property, located at 129 West 51st Street.
  - Estate inventory - personal property, [1920] (Box 22, Folder 8)
    List of items at One East 70th Street designated as personal property of Adelaide Frick or Helen Clay Frick.
  - Proposed sculpture gallery, 1915-1922 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence with Thomas Hastings and Charles Allom regarding the proposed addition of a sculpture gallery to One East 70th Street, which was never carried out. Folder includes reproductions of two details from the drawings for the proposed gallery. Also contains correspondence on matters unrelated to the addition.
  - Sidewalk repairs, 1922-1923 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    Contents concern a dispute with the city after flagstones were damaged outside the residence. Includes blueprint for a receiving basin and inlet at the corner of Fifth Avenue and 70th Street.
  - W. & J. Sloane dispute, 1918, 1924 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    Contains correspondence documenting a claim against W. & J. Sloane re: outstanding remittance for furnishings removed from the residence and sold on Frick's behalf.
- Series VIII: Daily Life, 1914-1931, undated
  This series contains contains materials documenting the Frick family's activities and interests, along with household operations and expenditures. Of particular note are the household diaries, 1914-1919, which record guests to the house, luncheons, dinners and other entertainments, purchase and installation of paintings and other works of art, and comings and goings of family members. This series also contains notebooks with monthly compilations of household payroll and bills paid, summaries of dinners given at the house (e.g. guest lists, menus, music, etc.), inventories of books, wines, and liquors, and information about employees who served the Frick family at One East 70th Street, Eagle Rock, and other locations.
  - Address book, circa 1914-1919 (Box 22, Folder 12)